A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Judgments and Criminal Suits, 1783-1896 (bulk 1786-1859)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Arlington County (Va.) Judgments and Criminal Suits, 1783-1896 (bulk 1786-1859)
The Library of Virginia
0007339661, 0007442060, 1015218-1154013, 1188950 circa
63 cu.ft (119 boxes)
Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Arlington County.
Historical Information
Arlington County was originally named Alexandria County. It was formed from a portion of Fairfax County that Virginia in 1789 ceded to the federal government for use as the site of a new national capital. In 1801 the area officially became part of the District of Columbia, although Congress named it Alexandria County. By an act of 9 July 1846, Congress returned the county to Virginia, and the General Assembly extended the commonwealth's jurisdiction over the region effective 20 March 1847. By an act of assembly passed 16 March 1920, the county's name was changed to Arlington, the name of the Custis family mansion (the home of Robert E. Lee), which is located in the county. An urban county, Arlington contains no incorporated towns or cities. The county courthouse is in the county.
Scope and Content
Arlington County (Va.) Judgments and Criminal Suits, 1783-1896 (bulk 1786-1859), consist primarily of civil suits and commonwealth causes heard in the Hustings Court of Alexandria and the Circuit Court of the District of Columbia. The majority of civil suits relate to matters of debt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Mathews County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Civil procedure--Virginia--Arlington County.; Crime--Virginia--Arlington County.; Debt--Virginia--Arlington County.; Free African Americans--Virginia--Arlington County.; Marine insurance--Virginia--Arlington County.; Merchant mariners--Virginia--Arlington County.; Public records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Slavery--Virginia--Arlington County.
Geographical Names:
Alexandria County (Va.)--History.; Arlington County (Va.)--History.; Washington (D.C.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Criminal court records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Local government records--Virginia--Arlington County.
Contents List
- Catherine Flood McCall vs. Francis Eve, 1804 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015233)
  To recover the penalty imposed by law for carrying a slave out of the Commonwealth of Virginia without consent of owner. Runaway slave named Charles. Depositions included.
- John and James Tucker vs. Marine Insurance Co., 1804 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145625)
  Involves Spanish piracy.
- James Young vs. Marine Insurance Co., 1806 March., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145630)
  Goods lost due to hurricane in Jamaica. New York newspaper used as exhibit.
- Admx. of Maurice Herlihy vs. Trst(s) of Roman Catholic Church, 1806 July., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145631)
  Suit related to construction of a Roman Catholic Church building in Alexandria.
- Samuel Crowdson and Co. vs. John W. Leonard, 1806 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145638)
  Ship captured by British man of war. One sailor impressed. Goods seized.
- William Hodgson vs. Marine Insurance Co., 1807 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Box 1145645)
  Ship captured by British man of war. Ship and goods sold by British
- Anthony Crease vs. George Parker, 1808 July., Extent: 1 folder. (Box 1145646)
  Defendant was a former slave who borrowed money from plaintiff to pay for his freedom.
- Christopher Fry vs. William Yeaton, 1808 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015247)
  Ship captured by British man of war and French privateer.
- William Short vs. John Brown Cutting, 1808 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015247)
  Short was minister to Holland, Spain, and Russia. Includes correspondence re: international political environment. He was close to Thomas Jefferson. Cutting was an attorney for impressed American seaman in London. Also associated with Jefferson.
- Christopher Fry vs. Thomas Vowell, Jr., 1809 July., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015242)
- Christopher Fry vs. John G. Ladd, 1809 July., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015242)
- Thomas Willock vs. Marine Insurance Co., 1809 July., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145649)
- United States vs. John Duffy, 1809 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145651)
  (Writ of Habeas Corpus) Duffy was arrested and jailed for attempting to murder members of his family. He was accused of putting ratsbane in a kettle of boiling water for tea to be drank at supper.
- William Yeaton vs. Marine Insurance Co., 1811 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145661)
  Ship damaged by weather.
- Admr. of James Wilson vs. Robert Young, 1811 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145662)
- Admr. of James Park vs. Abel Willis, 1813 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145669)
  Involves runaway slave.
- Simon Sommers vs. Bolitha Laws, 1814 April., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145670)
- Mutual Assurance Society vs. Ferdinando Fairfax, 1814 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145671)
  Insurance policies includes drawings of buildings owned by Fairfax including slave quarters.
- James Grady vs. James Hammond, 1815 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015256)
  Defendant accused of beating plaintiff's slave whereby he lost his services.
- Grayson, Steel, and Williams vs. Thomas Ewell, 1816 April., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1145675)
  suit involves gunpowder factory and Navy Department.
- Wiliam N. Mills vs. Alexander Tatterson, 1816 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015257)
- Mary Fendall vs. Edward Lloyd, 1816 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015258)
  Defendant accused of beating plaintiff's slave.
- Joseph Birch vs. Andrew Bartle, 1816 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1015258)
- United States vs. Justices of Alexandria County, 1817 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154001)
  County jail declared to be a nuisance.
- Samuel Chauncey vs. William Yeaton, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154004)
  Ship captured by British man of war.
- Thomas Lund Washington vs. William Wilson, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154004)
  Involves runaway slave. Defendant (a shipmaster) removed slave from Washington D.C. without plaintiff's permission. Includes correspondence from slave.
- James Watson vs. Robert Hall, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154004)
  Involves runaway slaves who were married.
- Catharine C. Allison vs. Thomas Longden, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154004)
- Richard H. Love vs. Washington Boyd, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154005)
  Involves runaway slave named Jane or Jane Williams. Relates to a freedom suit, Jane vs. Richard Love.
- Jane H. Slocum vs. Amos Smith, 1818 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154005)
  Involves runaway slave named Davey Payne. He served on ship commanded by Smith. Includes correspondence.
- James Mitchell, etc. vs. Nathaniel Freeman, 1819 Oct.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154009)
  Plaintiffs were sailors who served under Freeman. They sued for their pay.
- State of Maryland vs. Potomac Co., 1820 April., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1154012)
  Suit involves lottery for improving navigation of Potomac and Shenandoah rivers.
- United States vs. Leven Gales, 1821 May., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043562)
  Defendant was a free black. Charged and found guilty of seducing a slave named Fielder by means of false papers to abscond from the estate of his master, Bushrod Washington. He attempted to pass off Fielder as his nephew.
- United States vs. Emily, a slave, 1821 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043561)
  Defendant was charged with attempted to destroy her infant child.
- Sampson Sumly vs. Solomon Lorins, 1822 May., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043561)
  Plaintiff was a free person of color. He sued the defendant, a sea captain, for taking off the plaintiff's son, a minor aged 20, without his consent and having him in another state, or in this case, the West Indies. Plaintiff sued for loss income ($2000) he would have made from his son's employment as a caulker. The jury awarded him $45 depending on the judge's opinion. The judge sided with the defendant.
- David Black, etc. vs. Charles Bradford, 1823 May., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043565)
  Defendant accused of obstructing the plaintiff's ancient lights.
- Richard Gardner vs. Columbian Insurance Company, 1824 May., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043569)
  Large suit involving ship sank in Rio Janeiro. Numerous exhibits and depositions. Mutiny perhaps involved.
- Christian Clarke vs. Corporation of Washington, 1827 April., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043575)
  Plaintiff suing for the $100,000 he won in a national lottery sponsored by city of Washington, D.C. Winning ticket used as exhibit. Background on lottery. Case heard in Supreme Court.
- Ashby and Stribling vs. Columbian Insurance Company, 1828 April., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043576)
  Large suit involving ship sank by bad weather, perhaps a hurricane. Numerous exhibits and depositions. Newspaper used as exhibit by plaintiff. American Beacon, 1825 June 18.
- Samuel H. Smith vs. Thomas K. Beale, 1838 Oct.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043590)
  Plaintiff was treasurer of Washington National Monument Society. Suit involves an agent of society responsible with collecting pledges for the Washington Monument in Alabama. Suit includes correspondence from agent detailing his travels and travails in Alabama.
- United States vs. William Hudland, 1838 Nov.., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1043590)
  Includes Presidential pardon signed by Martin Van Buren.